Hazel E. Mills Papers, 1816-1938 MS 446
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Hazel E. Mills Papers 1816-1938
Colelction Number: MS 446
Mills Hazel E., 1910-1999
1.5 Linear Feet
Research notes, newspaper clippings and maps, 1816-1938. The bulk of the material is handwritten research notes related to the navigation of the Colorado River. Some of the notes are contained in a card index. The notes include article summaries compiled for Mills’ proposed dissertation, Navigation of the Colorado River and its effect on the development of the Arizona frontier. The maps are tracings done by Mills.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None.
Mills, Hazel E., "The Arizona Fleet," American Neptune, I, 3 (July 1941), 255-74.
Biographical Note
Hazel Emery was born in Pomona, California on October 29, 1910. She lived on a ranch near Chino, California. Then the family moved to Long Beach. Hazel married Randall Vause Mills on December 13, 1931 in Berkeley, California. Both were writers about Oregon history.
Hazel did her undergraduate work at the University of California at Berkeley studying English. Hazel attended library school and subsequently worked for the Washington State Library in Olympia. Her book, Frances Fuller Victor: the Witness to America’s Westerings, was published in 2002 by the Oregon Historical Society. Hazel died July 2, 1999 in Eugene, OR.
This Collection is organized into 2 series.
Series List
Series I: Research notes, 1816-1938
Series II: Card index, 1850-1909
Research notes, newspaper clippings and maps, 1816-1938. The bulk of the material is handwritten research notes related to the navigation of the Colorado River. Some of the notes are contained in a card index. The notes include article summaries compiled for Mills’ proposed dissertation, Navigation of the Colorado River and its effect on the development of the Arizona frontier. The maps are tracings done by Mills.
Boats; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Colorado River-- Exploration and discovery; Colorado River-- Navigation; Ferries; Freight ships; Frontier and pioneer life--Arizona; Historic mines; Mills, Hazel E, 1910-1999; Mining districts--Arizona; Mining districts--Colorado; Railroad travel; River steamboats; Stagecoach lines; Steam--navigation; Trade routes; Waterways
- Series I: Research notes,1816-1938
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  It contains article summaries compiled for Mills’ proposed dissertation, Navigation of the Colorado River and its effect on the development of the Arizona frontier. It also includes newspaper clippings and notes on Colorado River navigation and Colorado River maps traced by Mills.
  - Colorado River maps Arizona and Southwest traced by Hazel E Mills, 1816-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Compilations of date and working notes on steamboats, navigation, commerce, captains’ places, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation notes - Article summaries A-F, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dissertation notes - Article summaries G-L, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation notes - Article summaries M-Z, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation notes - Summary of proposed dissertation and bibliography of primary resources, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1933; 1938,; undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes from newspapers Colorado River navigation taken by Hazel E. Mills, 1852-1876 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Card Index, 1850-1909
  This series contains notes taken by Mills. Box 2 is arranged alphabetically by newspaper name and chronologically within each publication. Box 3 is arranged by topic and by author.
  - Notes are from the following newspapers:, 1850-1890 (Box 2)
    - Arizona Miner
    - Arizona Sentinel
    - Los Angeles Star
    - Oregon Argus
    - Oregonian
    - San Francisco Alta California
  - Topics include Biography, Boats, Colorado River, Commerce, Indians, Mines, Miscellaneous, Place names, Travel routes, Transportation companies, River boats and steamships. Notes are from the following newspapers,:, 1853-1909 (Box 3)
    - Alta California
    - Arizona Sentinel
    - Arizona Gazette
    - Arizona Weekly Enterprise
    - Arizona Miner
    - San Diego World
    - Los Angeles Star